You may have heard the phrase
你或许听说过
《数学在自然科学中不可思议的有效性》
The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Mathematics in the Natural Sciences.
This was the title of a paper
这是一篇论文的标题
by the physicist Eugene Wigner
作者是物理学家  尤金·魏格纳
尤金·魏格纳
but even more fun than the title
比标题更有意思的
is the way that he chooses to open it.
是他选择的开头
The paper begins quote,
论文开头写道
"There is a story about two friends who were classmates in high school...
“从前有两个好朋友  她们是高中同学…
talking about their jobs
两人谈论起如今的工作
One of them became a statistician
其中一人当了统计学家
and was working on population trends.
正在研究人口趋势
They showed a reprint to their former classmates
统计学家拿出一篇文章给老同学看
and the reprint started as usual with the Gaussian distribution.
开篇就是一个平淡无奇的正态分布
The statistician explained to the former classmate
统计学家向自己的老同学逐一解释
the meaning of the symbols for
那些式子表示的含义——
the actual population, the average population and so on.
实际人口、平均人口…等等
The classmate was a bit incredulous
同学有点怀疑
and was not quite sure whether the statistician was pulling their leg.
不确定统计学家是不是在捉弄她
"How can you know that?" was the query
“你是怎么知道的？”  她问
and "What is this symbol over here?"
“那里的那个符号又是什么？”
"Oh", said the statistician.
“噢”  统计学家回答
"This is π."
“这是 π”
"What is that?"
“π 是什么？”
"The ratio of the circumference of a circle to its diameter."
“圆的周长和直径的比值”
"Well, now you're pushing the joke too far.", said the classmate.
“啊这  你这玩笑太过分了”  同学说
"Surely, the population has nothing to do with the circumference of the circle."
“……人口又怎么可能跟圆的周长扯上关系呢！”
In the paper, Wigner then goes on to talk about
在他这篇论文中  魏格纳接下来讨论了
the more general phenomenon of concepts in pure math
在纯数学领域  普遍存在的一个现象：
《数学在自然科学中不可思议的有效性》
seeming to find applications that extend strangely beyond
纯数学有许多概念  应用得似乎太广了
what their definitions would suggest.
远远超出了原本的定义
But I would like to stay focused on this particular anecdote
但我想继续关注这段轶事中
圆跟人口有什么关系？
and the question that the statistician's friend is getting at.
这位统计学家的朋友提出的问题
You see, there is a very beautiful and classic proof
有一个美妙的经典证明
泊松的经典证明
that explains the π inside the formula for a normal distribution
解释了正态分布的式子中离奇出现的 π
and despite there being a number of other really great explanations online
虽然网上已经有了无数相当酷炫的解释
see some links in the description
相关链接请看评论区
泊松的经典证明
神秘常数
I cannot help but indulge in
但我还是忍不住在这里
the pleasure of reanimating it here.
不厌其烦地将它重新演绎一遍
For one thing, there is a fun side note that
一方面  很有意思的是
维度
n维球的体积
n维球的边界的体积
I didn't learn until recently about how you can use this proof
我最近才知道  可以利用这个证明思路
to derive the volumes of higher dimensional spheres.
来求出高维空间中球的体积
But much more importantly than that, what I really want to do
但更重要的  也是我真正想做的
is try to go beyond the classic proof.
是努力超越这个经典证明
Consider this hypothetical statistician's friend.
面对这个故事中统计学家的朋友
……人口又怎么可能跟圆的周长扯上关系呢！
What I want to ask is,
我想问的是
can we find an explanation that would satisfy their disbelief?
能否找到让这位朋友心悦诚服的解答？
怎么解释才能让人相信？
You see, they're not just asking for some pure math proof
毕竟  这位朋友想要的不是用数学去证明
about a function that was handed down to them on high.
一个从天而降的函数的性质
The friend's incredulity
她真正不相信的
was that circles should have anything to do with population statistics.
是 “圆” 和 “人口统计” 之间的关联
人口统计
Until we fully draw that connecting line,
在完全呈现这种关联之前
we should consider the task incomplete.
我们需要回顾之前未完成的任务
Those of you who watched the last video on the Central Limit Theorem
看过之前中心极限定理那期视频的观众们
中心极限定理
will have some of the backdrop here
可能已经了解了一些背景知识
because there we broke down the formula for a normal distribution,
因为在那期视频里  我们剖析了正态分布
正态分布
正态分布(也叫高斯分布）
which is also called a Gaussian Distribution
或称高斯分布的数学表达式
and when you strip away all of the different parameters and the constants,
剥去各种各样的参数和常量之后
the basic function that describes the bell curve shape is e^-x²
描述钟形曲线的基本函数  就是 e 的 -x² 次方
And the reason that π showed up in the final formula
而 π 之所以出现在最终的式子里
was that the area underneath this curve works out,
就是因为  这条曲线下的面积的值
as you will see in a couple minutes,
你们很快就会发现
to be the √π.
正是 l√(pi)
So, what that meant for us was that
因此  这就意味着
at some point we needed to divide out by that √π
我们需要除掉这个 l√(pi)
to make sure that the area under the curve is 1,
来确保曲线下的面积为 1
which is a requirement
满足这一点  我们才能将其视为概率分布
before you can interpret it as a probability distribution.
In the full formula that you would see, say in a stats book,
你在统计学课本里  看见的完整式子中
this gets mixed together with some of the other constants.
π 和一些其他常数搅在了一起
But in its purest form,
但在最纯粹的形式中
that π originates from the area underneath this curve.
π 来源于这条曲线下的面积
So, step number one for you and me
因此  我们要做的第一步就是
第一步 解释为什么e^(-x^2)下的面积是l√(pi)
is to explain that area.
阐明怎么求这个面积
But I want to emphasize it's not the last step.
但我要在此强调  这不是最后一步
To satisfy the question raised by that hypothetical statistician's friend,
为了回应统计学家的朋友的质疑
we need to go further.
我们不能止步于此
第二步 解释e^(-x^2)是从哪里来的
We need to also answer
我们还需要指出
why is it that this function e^-x² from is so special in the first place.
函数“e 的 -x² 次方”究竟为什么会如此特殊
I mean, there are lots of different formulas you could write down
你看  明明有许多不同的式子
that would give a shape that you know,
都能描述这种
vaguely bulges in the middle and tapers out on either side.
中间突起  两边平稳下降的形状
So why is it that this specific function
但为什么偏偏这个函数
holds such a special place in statistics?
在统计学中独领风骚？
To phrase our goal another way
换句话说  我们的目标是
第三步 把这一切与中心极限定理联系起来
can we find a connection
能否找到一种解释
between the proof that shows why π shows up
把“π 出现原因的证明”
and the Central Limit Theorem
和“中心极限定理”联系起来
which, as we talked about in the last video,
我们上期视频讲过
is the thing that explains
这个定理解释了
when you can expect a normal distribution to arise in nature.
正态分布何时会在自然地出现
So, with all of that is the goal
那么  带着这些目标
first things first, let's dig into the classic and very beautiful proof.
首先  我们来仔细看看经典而美妙的证明
泊松的经典证明
Alright. When you want to find the area underneath the curve,
好  要想求解曲线下的面积
the tool for doing that is an integral.
用到的数学工具自然是积分
As a quick reminder for how you might read this notation,
快速回顾一下  这个式子就是说
you might imagine approximating that area
你可以用曲线下的许多小矩形
with many different rectangles under the curve
去逼近所要求的面积
where the height of each such rectangle
每个小矩形的高  就是在那个点处的函数值
is the value of the function above that point,
in this case e^-x² for a certain input x
在这里就是给定 x 后   e 的 -x² 次方的值
and the width is some little number that we're calling dx.
矩形的宽是个很小的数  我们将其记为 dx
We need to add up the areas of all these rectangles
我们需要把所有矩形的面积加起来
for values of x ranging from -∞ up to ∞
x的范围取从 -∞ 到 ∞
and the use of that notation dx is kind of meant to imply
dx 这个记号就是在提醒你
you shouldn't think of any specific width
不要把小宽度看作是固定的
but instead you ask as the chosen width for your rectangle gets thinner and thinner,
而是去考虑  当选择的宽度越来越窄时
what does this sum of all those areas approach?
所有面积的和会趋于什么值
Of course, all of that is just notation
当然  这些都只是抽象记号
unless you provide a way to answer that question
关键是  要如何求出这个极限呢
and the magic of calculus is that it provides just that.
这个问题的答案  正是微积分的精髓
At least usually.
至少通常是能算的
至少...一般来说是算的
You see, usually the procedure here
通常的步骤是
would be to find some function
先去找到另一个函数
whose derivative is equal to the stuff we have on the inside, e^-x².
使得导数等于里头的被积函数   e 的 -x² 次方
导数
In other words, we want to find an antiderivative of that function.
换句话说  我们想求的是这个函数的原函数
原函数
The problem is, for this particular function,
问题在于  对这个函数而言
不可能！
it is provably not possible to find such an antiderivative.
可以证明  不可能找到这个原函数的表达式
It's a little weird and
听起来有点奇怪
啊？！
beyond the scope of what I want to talk about here.
也超过了这期视频的讨论范围
But basically, even though there exists an antiderivative,
虽然原函数本身是存在的
原函数
it is a well-defined function.
是一个有定义的函数
You cannot express what that antiderivative is using all our usual tools
但你就是没法把原函数表达成通常的函数
不能用以下函数来表达
like polynomial expressions, trig functions, exponentials
比如  多项式  三角函数  指数函数  等等
or any way to mix them together.
及其任意的组合
So, finding this area requires a bit of cleverness.
因此  求这个面积需要一点技巧
There needs to be a new trick that we bring to bear.
这里我们要整点新花招
And the first step to this trick is easily the most absurd.
第一步看起来尤为荒谬
We start by bumping things up one dimension,
我们先把这个式子提高一维
so that instead of asking for the area under a bell curve,
这样我们要求的就不再是钟形曲线下的面积
we ask for the volume underneath this kind of bell surface.
而是这样的钟形曲面下的体积
You could rightly ask,
你当然会问
"Why would you do that? Who ordered another dimension?"
“搞什么？谁指使你再加一个维度的？”
搞什么?
是谁加的维度?
And I'll admit, it's not terribly motivated right now
我也只能承认  现在的动机确实不太充分
other than to say watch what happens when we just try it.
只能走一步看一步  看看会发生什么
嗯  待会就知道了
And in general with hard problems,
大而化之  对于难题
it's never a bad idea to try solving "cousins" of the problem
先尝试解决类似的问题  也不失为一个好主意
不妨试试类似的问题
since that can help you get a little bit of momentum and insight.
因为这能给你多一点动力和启发
To be clear on how this higher dimensional function is defined
我们来理清这个高维函数是如何定义的
it takes in two different inputs, X and Y,
它有两个变量 x 和 y
which we might think of as a point on the XY plane
我们可以视其为 XY 平面上的点
and the way to think about it is to consider
我们的思路是  考虑这个点到原点的距离
the distance from that point to the origin,
which I'll label as "r"
我将这个距离记为 r
and then to plug in that distance to our original bell curve function.
然后将这个距离  代入一开始的钟形曲线函数中
That is, we take e to the negative r².
我们得到了 e 的 -r² 次方
You might notice the lines I've drawn on this diagram
你可能会注意到我在图上所画的线
make a right triangle,
形成了一个直角三角形
so by the Pythagorean theorem, x²+y²=r².
所以根据勾股定理  x²+y²=r²
So, in the function I have written where you see x²+y²,
所以在上面所写的函数中  只要你看到 x²+y²
you can think in the back of your mind
你就可以把它当作
that's really the square of the distance from the point to the origin.
(x,y)点到原点距离的平方
The main thing to notice here is how this gives our function
注意看  这样定义的新函数
a kind of circular symmetry
自然就有了圆周对称性
int the sense that all of the inputs that sit on a given circle have the same output.
即  同一个圆上的所有点  函数值都相等
And so, when we graph this function in three dimensions,
并且这样一来  在三维空间中画函数曲面时
it means it has a rotational symmetry about the Z axis.
图像就具有关于 Z 轴的旋转对称性
Math tends to reward you when you respect its symmetries.
数学女神偏爱那些敬重她对称之美的人
So for a question of computing the volume underneath the surface,
所以为了计算这个曲面下方的体积
what we're going to do is respect that symmetry
我们要做的是利用对称性
and imagine integrating together
考虑对曲面下一系列同心圆筒进行积分
a bunch of thin little cylinders underneath that surface.
Here, making this a little more quantitative,
为了量化这个过程
let's focus on just one of those cylindrical shells,
我们首先关注一个固定的圆筒
where its area is going to be the circumference of that shell times the height.
其侧面积等于圆筒的周长乘以高度
侧面积= ( 周长 ) ( 高 )
You might imagine it as something like the label on a soup can
你可以把它想象成罐头上的标签纸
that we can unwrap into a rectangle.
我们可以把它展成一个矩形
The circumference of the cylinder,
这个圆筒的周长
which is the top side of that rectangle
也就是矩形的一边
is going to be 2 π times the radius.
等于 2π 乘上半径
And then the height of our cylinder,
而圆筒的高
the other side of our rectangle
对应着矩形的另外一边
is the height of the surface at this point,
正是曲面在这一点上的高度
which by definition
根据定义
is the value of our function associated with that radius,
就是我们的函数在该半径处的取值
which like I said earlier, you can think of as e to the negative r².
如我之前所说  函数值是 e 的 -r² 次方
Now the real way you want to think about this
实际上  圆筒不只有侧面积
is to give that a little bit of thickness
还有一个很小的厚度
which we will call "dr"
我们记作 dr
so that the volume that it represents
所以圆筒对应的体积
体积
is approximately that area we just looked at
近似为我们先前提到的侧面积
multiplied by this thickness, dr.
乘上这个厚度 dr
Our task now is to integrate together
我们现在的任务是对这些圆筒积分
or add together all of these different cylinders
或者说  将半径在 0 到 ∞ 之间的所有圆筒体积相加
as our ranges between zero and infinity.
Or more precisely, we consider what happens
更准确的说  我们考虑的是
as that thickness gets thinner and thinner approaching zero
圆筒越来越薄  厚度 dr 趋于 0 的情形
and we add together the volumes of the many many many different
然后将这茫茫茫茫多的
thin cylinders that sit underneath that curve.
曲面下薄圆筒的体积相加
You might think "This is just a harder version of what we were looking at earlier. -
你可能觉得  这只是把开始的问题变得更困难了
Three dimensions should be more complicated than two."
三维应当比二维更复杂
But actually, something very helpful has happened.
但实际上  这时发生了一件好事情
First let me clean up a little by factoring the π outside that integral.
首先  可以整理一下  把 π 移到积分外面
Now the stuff inside that integral,
现在积分式内的部分
having picked up this term "2r"
因为多了个 2r
does have an antiderivative.
反而就有原函数了
We can now apply the usual tactics of calculus.
我们开始采用微积分的常规操作
Specifically, that whole inside expression
具体而言  积分符号中的部分是
is the derivative of negative e to the negative r².
负的（e 的 -r² 次方）的导数
And so, those of comfortable with calculus know what to do from here.
接着  熟悉微积分的观众已经知道怎么做了
We take that antiderivative
我们往这个原函数里面
and plug in the upper bound, which is negative infinity squared
代入积分上界  也就是负 e 的 -∞² 次方
and that gives us zero
得到 0
or speaking a little bit more precisely
或者更准确的说
if you consider the limit of this expression as the input approaches infinity,
考虑这个表达式在变量趋于无穷时的极限
the limiting value is zero
这个极限值为 0
and we subtract off the value of that antiderivative
然后再减去  原函数在积分下界 0 的取值
at the lower bound, zero,
which in this case is -1.
这里算出来是 -1
So, all in all, the whole integral just works out to be 1,
所以最终这个积分的结果就是 1
which means all we're left with is that factor out in front, π.
也就是说  整个式子留下的只有积分外的倍数 π
Evidently, the volume underneath this bell surface is π.
于是  这个钟型曲面下的体积就是 π
And I'll point out in this case it's not wild that π shows up
要指出的是   π 在这里出现并不奇怪
有圆周对称性的地方就有我们
体积
because the surface has this intrinsic circular symmetry.
因为这个曲面自带了圆的对称性
Still, you might wonder "How does that help us?"
不过你可能会问  “这有什么用？”
As I said, throughout math, if you face a hard problem,
如我之前所说  要想攻克数学中的难关
solving an adjacent problem can be unexpectedly helpful as a next step.
先解决一个相近的问题  说不定能铺平前路
And in this case it's helpful not just for building intuition
我们这个例子的意义不止是为了建立直觉
but we can directly relate the three dimensional graph
还能通过换一个算体积的观点
直接的联系
to our two dimensional graph
by analyzing the volume in a second different way.
直接联系起来三维与二维中的图像
You see, the more general way to approach volumes underneath surfaces
求曲面下体积更通用的方法是
is to think of chopping it up into slices
将它切分成一个个平行于坐标轴的薄片
that are all parallel to one of the axis.
For example, all these slices that are parallel to the X axis.
例如  画面中这些薄片就都平行于 x 轴
For example, this right here is a slice that corresponds to the plane y=0.
再比如  这一个切片对应着平面 y=0
You might notice it looks just like a bell curve
你或许会发现  它长得很像钟型曲线
and if we write out the function, this should actually make a lot of sense.
写出它的函数形式后  你就会发现确实如此
You could just plug in y=0,
直接代入 y=0 就行了
but to help see what happens with other slices,
但为了理解其它切片上的事情
notice how thanks to the rules of exponentiation,
注意这里利用指数运算的法则
we could also write function as e to the negative x² times e to the negative y².
我们可以将函数写作“e 的 -x² 次方”乘“e 的 -y² 次方”
It factors out nicely.
很完美的因式分解
On this slice, that e to the negative y²,
在这个切片上 e 的 -y² 次方
is just a number - specifically the number 1.
只是一个数  在这里具体等于 1
So this is the same graph we've seen before, e to the negative x²,
所以这和前面的图像相同  也就是 e 的 -x² 次方
meaning that the area of this slice
也就是说这个切片的面积
is exactly the thing that we're looking for.
就是我们最初要求的积分
神秘常数
It's the mystery constant which I'm going to give the name "C".
我们姑且称这个神秘常数为 C
What's nice is there is nothing really special about this particular slice.
很好的一点是  这个切片并没有什么特别的
If we chose a different slice corresponding to a different Y value,
如果我们选取 y 值不同的另一个切片
it corresponds to multiplying this curve by a different number.
就相当于将原本的曲线乘以另一个值
So, it's the same basic shape
所以这些曲线的形状都类似
just scaled down by that number.
只是高度被压缩了一个倍数
Meaning its area is the same as our mystery constant
因此  其面积就是神秘常数 C
just scaled down by some number.
再乘上一个压缩倍数
That's pretty cool.
这很带劲
Each one of these slices has the same basic shape
这些切面的基本形状都相同
just rescaled in the vertical direction.
只是在竖直方向被放缩了
Which by the way is not at all true for most two variable functions.
顺便一提  绝大多数二元函数并没有该性质
This is very much dependent on the fact
截面的缩放性质  实际取决于
that we were able to factor our function
我们能否把函数分离成
into one part that's just dependent on the Y
只依赖 y 变量的函数
and another part that's just dependent on the X.
乘以只依赖 x 变量的函数
Now, to think about the volume underneath this whole surface,
为了计算这个曲面下方的体积
here's another way we could phrase it.
我们可以这样来思考
We're going to compute another integral
下面我们来计算另一个
that ranges from Y equals negative infinity up to infinity
y 从 -∞ 到 ∞ 的积分
切片的面积
where the term inside that integral tells us the area of each one of those slices.
被积表达式描述的  是每一个切片的面积
And when we multiply it by a little thickness, dy,
我们把每个切片  乘以一个很小的厚度 dy
切片的体积
you might think of it as giving each one of those slices a little bit of volume.
可以看作每一个小切片  都有一个小体积
And remember, that term C sitting in front represents the thing we want to know.
记住  在前面的 C 项代表了我们想算的切片面积
Which itself is an integral. A suspiciously similar looking integral.
因此 C 本身也是一个积分  并且跟 y 的积分过于相似
See, if we take the expression on the top
看  如果我们从上面的表达式里
and we factor out that constant C because it's just a number, it doesn't depend on Y,
提取出常数 C 中—— 它是与自变量 y 无关的一个数
the thing we're left with, the integral we need to compute
那么我们所剩下的这个需要计算的积分
is exactly the mystery constant, the thing we don't know.
恰好又是神秘常数 C
So, overall, the volume underneath this bell surface
也就是说  这个钟型曲面下方的体积
works out to be this mystery constant squared.
就是神秘常数 C 的平方
Out of context, this might seem very unhelpful,
抛开上下文  这也许没有什么用
it's just relating one thing we don't know to another thing we don't know
我们只是把一个未知的东西  表达成另一个未知的东西
except we've already computed the volume under this surface.
但是  这个曲面下的体积  我们刚刚算过啊
We know that it's equal to π.
我们知道答案等于 π
Therefore, the mystery constant we want to know,
因此  这个我们最想计算的神秘常数 C
the area underneath this bell curve,
即正态分布曲线下方的面积
must be the square root of π.
必须等于 l√(pi)
It's a very pretty argument but a few things are not entirely satisfying.
这个论证非常漂亮  可惜不够令人满意
感觉像花招
For one thing, it feels a little bit like a trick,
一方面  这就像一个碰巧行得通的小花招
something that just happened to work
without offering much of a sense
学完后  你还是不知道怎样自己推出这个结论
自己得怎么想出来
for how you could have rediscovered it yourself.
你这玩笑太过分了
Also, if we think back to our imagined statistician's friend,
另一方面  回想统计学家的朋友
…人口又怎么可能跟圆的周长扯上关系呢?
it doesn't really answer their question,
这并没有回答她们的问题：
which was what do circles have to do with population statistics.
“圆”在人口统计学里有什么用
解释为什么e^(-x^2)下的面积是l√(pi)
解释e^(-x^2)是从哪里来的
把这一切与中心极限定理联系起来
Like I said, it's the first step, not the last;
我说过  这只是本视频的第一步
and as our next step, let's see if we can unpack
我们的下一步  就是试着解释
why this proof is not quite as wild and arbitrary as you might first think
为什么这证明并没有想象中那么蛮不讲理
and how it relates to an explanation for
以及如何与函数
where this function e^-x² is coming from in the first place.
“e 的 -x² 次方”的来源联系在一起
赫歇尔-麦克斯韦对高斯分布的推导
John Herschel was this mathematician/scientist/inventor
约翰·赫歇尔这位数学家/科学家/发明家
约翰·赫歇尔
who really did all sorts of things throughout the 19th century.
在十九世纪可谓是个全才
He made contributions in chemistry,
他的贡献横跨化学  天文学  影像学  植物学
astronomy, photography, botany,
he invented the blueprint
他发明了蓝图
and named many of the moons in our solar system
为太阳系里的诸多卫星取了名字
and in the midst of all of this,
除此之外  在 1850 年
he also offered a very elegant little derivation
他还提出了一种非常精巧的方式
这是怎么来的？
for the Gaussian distribution in 1850.
来推导正态分布的式子
the setup is to imagine that
他一上来先假设
you want to describe some kind of
你想描述二维空间里的某种概率分布
probability distribution in two dimensional space.
For instance maybe you want to model the probability density
例如  飞镖击中靶子各处的概率密度
for hits on a dartboard.
What Herschel showed
赫歇尔证明的是
is that if you want this distribution to satisfy
如果要让这个分布
two pretty reasonable seeming properties,
满足两个很合理的性质的话
your hand is unexpectedly forced
那实际上没有多少选择的余地了
and even if you had never heard of a Gaussian in your life,
就算你从来没听过正态分布
you would be inexorably drawn to use a function with the shape
只凭两个性质  也会不可避免地得到这种函数
e to the negative x² plus y².
也就是 e 的 -(x²+y²) 次方
You do have 1 degree of freedom
确实还有1个自由度
to control the spread of that distribution
用来控制这个分布有多分散
and of course, there's going to be some constant sitting in front
前面也当然会有个常数
to make sure it's normalized
来确保总体积是 1
but the point is that we're forced into this very specific kind of bell curve shape.
但无论如何 函数的形状必定是这种钟形
The first of these two properties
回到第一条要满足的性质
每个点的概率(密度)只取决于到原点的距离
is that probability density around each point
每个点的概率密度
depends only on its distance from the origin
只取决于与原点的距离
not on its direction.
而不取决于具体的方向
So, on a dartboard with everybody aiming for the bull's eye,
用瞄准靶心射击来举例的话
this would mean that you could rotate the board
这就意味着  靶子旋转之后
and it would make no difference for the distribution.
概率分布还是一样的
Mathematically, this means that
用数学语言来说的话
the function describing your probability distribution,
考虑这一分布的概率密度函数
which I'll call f₂ since it takes in two inputs, X and Y.
不妨记作 f₂(x,y)   因为有两个变量
Well, it can be expressed as
则 f₂ 可以改写成
某个单变量函数
some single variable function of the radius, r.
只关于半径 r 的单变量函数
And just to spell it out,
重新明确一下
r is the distance between the point (x, y) and the origin,
这里的 r 表示 (x, y) 离原点的距离
the square root of x² plus y².
也就是 l√(x²+y²)
Property number 2 is that
第二个性质是
每个随机点的 x 值和 y 值相互独立
the X and Y coordinates of each point are independent from each other.
Which is to say, if you learn the X coordinate of a point,
也就是说  就算知道了一个点的横坐标 x
it would give you no information about the Y coordinate.
对点的纵坐标 y 来说  毫无信息量
The way this looks as an equation is that
这个性质表现在式子里
our function which describes the probability density
就是这个表示各个点概率密度的函数
around each point on the XY plane
can be factored into two different parts.
可以分离成两个函数的乘积
One of which can be purely written in terms of X.
其中一个只有 x 变量
This is the distribution of the X coordinate,
代表了横坐标值的概率分布
I'm giving it the name "g".
记作函数 g
And the other part is purely in terms of Y.
而另一个函数则只有 y 变量
This would be the distribution for the Y coordinate
代表纵坐标值的概率分布
which I'm temporarily calling "h".
暂时叫做函数 h 好了
But if you combine this with the assumption that things are radially symmetric,
但加上第一条假设  概率分布要径向对称
both of these should be the same distribution.
那 x 和 y 的分布就得相同了
The behavior on each axis should look the same.
也意味着两个轴上概率分布完全相同
So we could also write this as g(x)g(y).
于是这个式子可以写成 g(x)g(y)
It's the same function.
因为 g 恒等于 h
And more than that, this function is actually going to
不仅如此  其实这个 g(x)g(y)
be proportional to the one we were just looking at.
还跟我们刚才考虑的 f 函数成正比
The one that describes our probability density
就是自变量为半径 r
as a function of the radius,
the distance away from the origin.
的概率密度函数 f(r)
To see this, imagine you were to analyze a point that was on the X axis,
例如  假设有个 X 轴上的点
a distance r away from the origin.
离原点的距离是 r
Then the two distinct ways to express our function
那这两个基于不同性质构造的
based on the two different properties tells us that
截然不同的概率分布函数形式
f(r) has to equal some constant multiplied by g(r).
表明了 f(r) 等于 g(r) 乘上一个常数
某个常数
So these functions f and g are basically the same thing,
也就说明了  函数 f 和 g 算是一种东西
just up to some constant multiple.
只是差个常数倍
你猜要是怎样就最好
And you know what?
这时我就想了
It would be really nice if we could just assume that that constant was 1
直接说这个常数是 1 该多好啊
每个点的概率(密度)只取决于到原点的距离
每个随机点的 x 值和 y 值相互独立
so that f and g were literally the same function
这样 f 和 g 不就完全相等了嘛
and what I'm going to do, which might feel a little bit cheeky
虽然很不要脸
is just assume that that is the case.
但我想说我就是要这么做
What this means is that our answer is going to be a little bit wrong.
但这样的话  算出来的答案也就不这么准确了
The function that we will deduce describing this distribution
我们得出的概率分布函数
will be off by some constant factor.
跟正确答案会差常数倍
But that's no big deal because in the end,
但这根本就不是个问题
we can just rescale to make sure the area under the curve is 1
最后我们还是得像其它概率分布一样
like we always do with probability distributions.
缩放一下  确保函数曲线下面积为 1
Now, if f and g are the same thing,
有了 f 和 g 等价
this gives us a very nice little equation purely in terms of the function f.
就能得到这个只用 f 表示的式子
Remember what this function f is.
重复一下这个函数的含义
If you have some point in the XY plane, a distance r from the origin,
假设平面上有一个离原点距离为 r 的点
then f(r) tells you the
那么 f(r) 表示的是
relative likelihood of that point showing up in the random process.
这个点在随机过程中出现的相对概率
More specifically, it gives the probability density of that point.
也可以说成是这个点的概率密度
At the outset, this function could have been anything.
一般来说  这个函数具体是什么并没有过多限制
But Herschel's two different properties
但赫歇尔这两个性质
每个点的概率(密度)只取决于到原点的距离
每个随机点的 x 值和 y 值相互独立
evidently implies something kind of funny about it.
显然某种程度上影射了它的函数形式
Which is that if we take the X and Y coordinates of that point on the plane
也就是说  取平面上一个点的坐标 (x,y)
and evaluate this function on them separately, taking f(x) times f(y)
分别计算 f(x) 和 f(y) 再乘起来
it should give us the same result.
结果应该和 f(r) 一致
Or if you prefer, we could expand out the meaning of
你也可以把距离 r 展开成 l√(x²+y²)
that distance r as the square root of X² plus Y²
and this is what our key equation looks like.
得到一个关键的式子
This kind of equation is what's known in the business as a Functional Equation.
这种方程  内行的叫法是“函数方程”
函数方程
We're not solving for an unknown number.
我们不是在求解一个未知数x
Instead we're saying that the equation is true for all possible numbers X and Y
而是已知这个等式对所有的 x 和 y 都成立
and the thing we're trying to find is an unknown function.
我们要找的是满足条件的未知函数 f(x)
In the back of your mind, you can think we already know
在脑海中  我们已经知道了
例如
one function that satisfies this property,
有一个函数满足这个性质
E to the negative X².
那就是 e 的 -x² 次方
And as a sanity check,
检查一下
you might verify for yourself that it does satisfy that.
你会发现  函数确实满足这个方程
Of course, the point is to pretend that you don't know that
当然  重点是你要假装自己不知道这个函数
and to instead deduce what all of the functions are which satisfy this property.
然后去推导  满足这个性质的函数都有哪些
你怎么样去近似求解呢？
In general, functional equations can be quite tricky.
一般来说  函数方程没那么好解
But let me show you how you can solve this one.
但这个方程我们可以这么求解
First it's nice to introduce a little helper function that I'll call h(x)
首先  我们引入一个辅助函数 h(x)
which will be defined as our mystery function
定义为我们要求的函数 -
evaluated at the square root of X.
在 l√x  点处的值
Said another way, h(x²) is the same thing as f(x).
换句话说  h(x²) 就等于 f(x)
For example, in the back of your mind
例如  在脑海中
where you know that e^-x² will happen to be one of the answers,
你知道 e 的 -x² 次方  已经是一个解
this little helper function h would be e^-x.
那么它对应的辅助函数 h 就是 e⁻ˣ
But again, we're pretending like we don't know that.
不过我们现在还是假装不知道答案
The reason for doing this is that
引入辅助函数的原因是
the key property for f looks a little bit nicer
这会使函数 f 的关键性质变得更好看
if we phrase it in terms of this helper function, h.
如果我们用 h 来表达 f 的性质
'Cuz now what it's saying is if you take two arbitrary positive numbers
这个性质现在表示的就是  任取两个正数
输入量相加
and you add them up and evaluate h,
先相加再代入函数 h
it's the same thing as evaluating h on them separately
结果等于  先分别代入函数 h  再相乘
输出量相乘
and then multiplying the results.
In a sense, it turns addition into multiplication.
可以说   h 将加法变成了乘法
Some of you might see where this is going
有些观众可能已经有头绪了
but let's take a moment to walk through
但我们还是先花时间过一遍
why this forces our hand.
这性质为什么定死了答案
As a next step, you might want to pause and convince yourself that
接下来  你可能需要暂停一下并搞清楚
if this property is true for the sum of two numbers,
如果这个性质对于两个正数的和成立
this property also must be true if we add up an arbitrary number of inputs.
那么  将任意 n 个数相加再代入 h   这个性质依旧成立
To get a feel for why this is so constraining,
为了感受一下这个约束条件有多强
think about plugging in a whole number, something like h(5).
我们代入一个具体数值  比如求 h(5)
Because you can write five as one plus one plus one plus one plus one,
因为你可以将 5 写成 1+1+1+1+1
this key property means that it
这个关键的性质意味着
must equal h(1) multiplied by itself five times.
h(5) 一定等于 h(1) 与自己相乘五次的结果
Of course, there's nothing special about five,
当然  这里的 5 并无特殊之处
I could have chosen any whole number N
我们可以选择任何整数 N
and we'd be forced to that the function
然后我们带入函数 h 中
looks like some number raised to the power N,
结果就等于 h(1) 的 N 次方
and let's go ahead and give that number a name
我们直接给这个 h(1) 取个名字
like "b" for the base of our exponential.
记作 b   表示指数函数的底数
As a little mini exercise here,
接下来有一个小练习
see if you can pause and take a moment to convince yourself that
暂停并思考一下  看看你能不能证明
习题：证明该等式对有理数x=p/q仍成立
the same is true for a rational input.
这个结论对于有理数也同样成立
That if you plug in p/q to this function,
也就是说  如果你把 p/q 代入函数
it must look like this base b^p/q.
结果也一定和 b 的 p/q 次方相等
And as a hint, you might want to think about
再给一个小提示  你或许会需要考虑
提示，考虑一下 h(p/q + ... + p/q )
adding that input to itself q different times.
将这个 p/q 与自己相加 q 次
And then because rational numbers are dense in the real number line,
接下来因为有理数在实数轴上是稠密的
if we make one more pretty reasonable assumption that
如果我们再做一个挺合理的假设
假设f（与h）为连续函数...
we only care about continuous functions,
假设我们只关心连续函数
this is enough to force your hand completely and say that
这就足够迫使我们得出结论
h has to be an exponential function, b^x for all real number inputs x.
h 一定是指数函数   h(x) = bˣ
对任意
I guess to be more precise, I should say for all positive real inputs.
更准确点  我应该说 b 和 x 都是正实数
The way we defined h it's only taking in positive numbers.
我们定义的函数 h 本来就只接受正数
Now, as we've gone over before,
接着  上期视频也讨论过
instead of writing down exponential functions as some base raised to the power x,
与其把指数函数写为某个底数 b 的 x 次方
某常数
mathematicians often to write them as e to the power of some constant c times x.
数学家们更爱写 e 的“常数 c 乘以 x”次方
Making the choice to always use e as a base
一直选用 e 作为底数
while letting that constant c determine
再用参数 c 来确定
which specific exponential function you are talking about
你讨论的是哪个具体的指数函数
just makes everything much easier anytime calculus comes wandering along your path.
这样万一要做微积分的计算  也会变得更方便
And so, this means that our target function f
同样  这也意味着我们的目标函数 f
has to look like e^cx².
应该是“e 的 cx² 次方”这样的形式
The beauty is that that function is no longer something
这套推导的好处在于  这个函数不再是凭空而来
that was merely handed down to us from on high.
Instead, we started these two different premises
我们是从两个前提条件出发
for how we wanted a distribution in two dimensions to behave
寻找我们想要的二元概率分布
and we were drawn to the conclusion that
并且我们得到的结论是
两条性质必然蕴含
the shape of the expression describing that distribution
这个分布的密度可以表示为一个
as a function of the radius away from the origin
以半径 r 为自变量的函数
has to be e to the power of some constant times that radius squared.
且形式一定是 e 的（常数 c 乘以半径 r 平方）次方
You remember I said earlier this answer will be off by a factor of a constant.
你应该记得我之前说过  这个答案还会差一个常数
We need to rescale it to make it a valid probability distribution
我们要缩放常数   使整个函数成为真正的概率分布
and geometrically, you might think of that as scaling it
从几何上讲  你可以认为缩放后
so that the volume under the surface is equal to 1.
曲面下方的体积必须等于 1
Now you notice that for positive values of this constant in the exponent c,
可以注意到  如果指数中的常数 c 为正值
our function blows up to infinity in all directions.
函数就会在所有方向上都膨胀到无穷大
So, the volume under that surface would be infinite,
因此  曲面下方的体积就会是无穷大的
meaning it's not possible to renormalize.
意味着我们不可能将其归一化
You can't turn it into a probability distribution
也就无法把它变成一个概率分布
and that leaves us with the last constraint
这就是最后一个约束条件
which is that this constant in the exponent has to be a negative number
指数中的常数c  必须是一个负值
and the specific value of that number determines the spread of the distribution.
并且这个特定的常数决定了分布的分散度
10 years after Herschel wrote this,
在赫歇尔写下这个结论十年后
詹姆斯·克拉克·麦克斯韦
James Clerk Maxwell, who's most well known for having written down
以写下电与磁的基本方程而闻名的麦克斯韦
the fundamental equations for electricity and magnetism,
independently stumbled across the same derivation.
也刚好独立地进行了相同的推导
In his case, he was doing it in three dimensions
但他考虑的是三维空间中的分布
since he was doing statistical mechanics and he was deriving
因为他当时正在研究统计力学
a formula for the distribution for velocities of molecules in a gas,
需要推导气体中分子速度分布的公式
but the logic all works out the same.
但背后的逻辑都是一样的
赫歇尔-麦克斯韦推导
径向对称
各坐标轴变量互相独立
For you and me, if we view this as the defining property of a Gaussian,
如果我们认为  这两个性质定义了高斯分布的话
如果用它来定义高斯分布
then it's a little bit less surprising that π might make an appearance.
那么 π 的出现也就不那么意外了
After all, circular symmetry was part of this defining property.
毕竟  圆形对称也是这个定义性质的一部分
More than that, it makes the clever proof that we saw earlier
更重要的是  它让我们之前看到的美妙证明
feel a little bit less out of the blue.
变得不那么出乎意料
I mean, a key problem solve principle in math
你看  数学中有个关键的解题原则是
is to use the defining features of your setup.
使用你开始时设定好的定义
And if you had been primed by this Herschel/Maxwell derivation
如果你跟上了 赫歇尔-麦克斯韦 的推导
where the defining property for a Gaussian
其中为高斯分布设的定义性质是
is this coincidence of having a distribution
这一类分布  需要同时满足
that's both radially symmetric and also independent along each axis,
1.径向对称性  与  2.各坐标独立分布
then the very first step of our proof which seemed so strange,
那么在我们的证明中  看着很奇怪的第一步
bumping the problem up one dimension,
即  将问题提升一个维度
was really just a way of opening the door
实际上就是在打开一扇门
to let that defining property make itself visible.
方便具体体现两条定义性质
And if you think back,
如果你回想一下
the essence of the came down to using that radial symmetry on the one hand
证明的核心  一方面利用了函数的径向对称性
and then also using the ability to factor the function on the other.
而另一方面则利用了函数可分解的性质
From this standpoint, using both those facts
从这个角度来看  使用这两个事实
feels less like a trick that happens to work
感觉就不那么像是碰巧的小把戏
and more like an inevitable necessity.
而更像是不可避免的步骤
Nevertheless, thinking once again of our statistician's friend,
然而  再次回想起统计学家的朋友
this is still not entirely satisfying.
这仍然不完全令人满意
Using the Herschel/Maxwell derivation,
赫歇尔-麦克斯韦的推导
saying this property of a multi-dimensional distribution is what defines a Gaussian,
以及  用高维分布的两个性质去定义高斯分布
但这假设了我们在2维啊
well that presumes that we're already in
首先要求我们已经处在某种多维情形中
some kind of multi-dimensional situation in the first place.
Much more commonly, the way that a normal distribution arises in practice
通常来说  实际上正态分布出现的情形
那中心极限定理怎么说?
doesn't feel spatial or geometric at all.
感觉跟空间与几何不相干
It stems from the central limit theorem
而是来源于中心极限定理
which is all about adding together many different independent variables.
讲的都是关于将许多独立的随机变量相加
解释为什么e^(-x^2)下的面积是l√(pi)
解释e^(-x^2)是从哪里来的
把这一切与中心极限定理联系起来
So to bring it all home here, what we need to do is explain
因此  回到最开始  我们需要去解释
why the function that's characterized by this Herschel/Maxwell derivation
为什么这个  赫歇尔-麦克斯韦的推导所刻画的函数
should be the same thing as
会等价于  中心极限定理中最核心的函数  呢
the function that sits at the heart of the central limit theorem.
And at this point, those of you following along
看到这里  跟随我一路看下来的观众
are probably going to make fun of me.
可能会来取笑我
I think it makes sense to pull this last step as its own video.
虽然我认为把最后一步单独做成视频是有意义的
卷积
下次一定...
I realise this is what?
不过我意识到这…
中心极限定理
The third time in a row that I've kicked this particular can down the road.
已经是我第三次把这话题鸽到下一期了
再下一次一定...
l√(pi)怎么来的?
这次真的一定
You see, the thing I'm building up to here
要知道  我所铺垫的下一期内容
involves a combination of the topics from the last three videos -
将同时涉及到这三期视频的主题
Convolutions, the Central Limit Theorem
卷积  中心极限定理
and now the Herschel/Maxwell characterization of normal distributions.
以及  赫歇尔/麦克斯韦对正态分布的刻画
The traditional explanation that I first learned to explain
我第一次学会的传统解释方法解释了
why e^-x² arises in the central limit theorem
为什么 e 的 -x² 次方会出现在中心极限定理中
has to do with fourier transforms and the convolution theorem
用到了傅里叶变换和卷积定理
and it's nice enough, don't get me wrong,
别误会  我并不是说那个证明不好
but what I'd like to try is to share a more elementary description
只是我希望分享一个更为初等的证明
that's based on this circular symmetry.
而且会妙用圆形对称性
The hope is that, together with this video,
我希望  结合这期视频
it offers a more visceral satisfaction for why that particular function arises
搞清楚这种函数的来龙去脉  能让你的满足感油然而生
and that maybe it offers something which would finally
并且这也可能会提供一些
address the incredulity from our statistician's friend.
最终解决我们统计学家朋友的疑问的想法
维度
n维球的体积
n维球的边界的体积
Oh and one final footnote here -
哦  还有最后一个脚注
after making a Patreon post about this particular project,
当在 Patreon 发布了一篇关于这个特定项目的推文后
one Patron who's a mathematician named Kevin Iga,
有位赞助者名叫 Kevin Iga，是一名数学家
shared something completely delightful that I'd never seen before,
Ta 分享了一些  让我大开眼界的美妙结果
which is that if you apply this integration trick in higher dimensions,
如果你在更高的维度上运用这个积分技巧
it lets you derive the formulas for volumes of higher dimensional spheres.
它可以带你推导出更高维球体的体积公式
It's a very fun exercise, I'm leaving the details up on the screen
这个练习非常有趣  我会将细节放在屏幕上
给想要挑战的观众留一些附加题
for any viewers who are comfortable with integration by parts.
能熟练运用分部积分的观众们  都可以来尝试一下
Thank you very much to Kevin for sharing that one.
非常感谢 Kevin 分享这一点
And thanks to all patrons by the way,
也顺便感谢所有赞助者
both for the support of the channel
感谢你们对于这个频道的支持
and also for all the feedback you offer on the early draft videos.
也感谢你们对于视频草稿提供的所有反馈